Chapter 75.
The right whale's head. Contrasted view.
Crossing the deck. Let us now have a good long look at the right whale's head.
As in general shape, the noble sperm whale's head may be compared to a Roman
war chariot, especially in front where it is so broadly rounded. So at a broad
view, the right whale's head bears a rather inelegant resemblance to a
gigantic gallottoed shoe. 200 years ago an old Dutch voyager likened its shape
to that of a shoemaker's last. And in this same last or shoe, that old woman
of the nursery tale with her swarming brood might very comfortably be lodged,
she and all her progeny.
But as you come nearer to this great head, it begins to assume different
aspects according to your point of view.
If you stand on its summit and look at these two F-shaped spout holes, you
would take the whole head for an enormous base vial and these spiracles
the apertures in its sounding board.
Then again, if you fix your eyes upon this strange crested comblike
incrustation on the top of the mass, this green barnacled thing which the
Greenlanders call the crown, and the southern fishers the bonnet of the right
whale, fixing your eyes solely on this, you would take the head for a trunk of
some huge oak with a bird's nest in its crotch. At any rate, when you watch
those live crabs that nestle here on this bonnet, such an idea will be almost
sure to occur to you, unless indeed your fancy has been fixed by the technical
term crown also bestowed upon it, in which case you will take great interest
in thinking how this mighty monster is actually a diademmed king of the sea,
whose green crown has been put together for him in this marvelous manner. But if
this whale be a king, he is a very sulky looking fellow to grace a diadem. Look
at that hanging lower lip. What a huge sulk and pout is there. A sulk and pout
by carpenters's measurement. About 20 ft long and 5 ft deep. A sulk and pout that
will yield you some 500 gallons of oil and more.
A great pity now that this unfortunate whale should be hair lipped. The fisher
is about a foot across. Probably the mother during an important interval was
sailing down the Peruvian coast when earthquakes cause the beach to gape.
Over this lip, as over a slippery threshold, we now slide into the mouth.
Upon my word, were I at Meno, I should take this to be the inside of an Indian
wigwam. Good lord, is this the road that Jonah went? The roof is about 12 feet
high and runs to a pretty sharp angle as if there were a regular ridge pole
there. While these ribbed, arched, hairy sides present us with those wondrous
halfvertical scimitar-shaped slats of whale bone, say 300 on a side, which
depending from the upper part of the head or crown bone, form those Venetian
blinds which have elsewhere been cursorally mentioned. The edges of these
bones are fringed with hairy fibers through which the right whale strains
the water, and in whose intricacies he retains the small fish, when openmouthed
he goes through the seas of brit in feeding time. In the central blinds of
bone, as they stand in their natural order, there are certain curious marks,
curves, hollows, and ridges, whereby some whalemen calculate the creature's
age, as the age of an oak by its circular rings. Though the certainty of
this criterion is far from demonstrable, yet it has the savor of analogical
probability. At any rate, if we yield to it, we must grant a far greater age to
the right whale than at first glance will seem reasonable.
In old times, there seemed to have prevailed the most curious fancies
concerning these blinds. One voyager in purchase calls them the wondrous
whiskers inside of the whale's mouth.
Another hogs bristles. A third old gentleman in Hackloot uses the following
elegant language. Quote, "There are about 250 fins growing on each side of
his upper chop which arch over his tongue on each side of his mouth." End quote.
Footnote. This reminds us that the right whale really has a sort of whisker, or
rather a mustache, consisting of a few scattered white hairs on the upper part
of the outer end of the lower jaw.
Sometimes these toughs impart a rather brigandish expression to his otherwise
solemn countenance. End of footnote.
As everyone knows, these same hogs bristles, fins, whiskers, blinds, or
whatever you please, furnish to the ladies their busks, and other stiffening
contrivances. But in this particular, the demand has long been on the decline.
It was in Queen Anne's time that the bone was in its glory, the farthingale
being then all the fashion. And as those ancient dams moved about gay, though in
the jaws of the whale, as you may say, even so in a shower, with like
thoughtlessness, do we nowadays fly under the same jaws for protection, the
umbrella being a tent spread over the same bone.
But now, forget all about blinds and whiskers for a moment, and standing in
the right whale's mouth, look around you, aresh, seeing all these colonades
of bone so methodically ranged about, would you not think you were inside of
the great Harlem organ, and gazing upon its thousand pipes? For a carpet to the
organ, we have a rug of the softest turkey, the tongue, which is glued, as
it were, to the floor of the mouth. It is very fat and tender and apt to tear
in pieces in hoisting it on deck. This particular tongue now before us, at a
passing glance, I should say it was a six barreler, that is, it will yield you
about that amount of oil.
He this you must have plainly seen the truth of what I started with, that the
sperm whale and the right whale have almost entirely different heads. To sum
up then, in the right whales there is no great well of sperm, no ivory teeth at
all, no long slender mandible of a lower jaw like the sperm whales. Nor in the
sperm whale are there any of those blinds of bone, no huge lower lip, and
scarcely anything of a tongue. Again, the right whale has two external spout
holes. The sperm whale only one.
Look your last now on these venerable hooded heads while they yet lie
together, for one will soon sink unrecorded in the sea, and the other
will not be very long in following.
Can you catch the expression of these sperm whales there? It is the same he
died with, only some of the longer wrinkles in the forehead now seem faded
away. I think his broad brow to be full of a prairieike placidity born of a
speculative indifference as to death.
But mark the other head's expression.
See that amazing lower lip pressed by accident against the vessel's side so as
firmly to embrace the jaw. Does not this whole head seem to speak of an enormous
practical resolution in facing death?
This right whale I take to have been a stoic? the sperm whale, a Plutonian who
might have taken up Spinosa in his latter years.